Very
well, we were talking about him. He
says
that the third level, the third level
of ethics, of the perfection of
morality, is
called morality or ethics that helps
other people. Well, so there is a
third level of
ethics. I just said it's the second. Well,
the first
is avoiding hurting other people. That's
the first morality. The second is doing good
with your morality. The
third—we have to clear the sound
here because I'm listening to this
old gentleman talking, which is right, it's me—the
third means taking
care of everyone, looking out for everyone.
He says that if
you want an example, we can
say what I'm saying. There are
four
ways to treat your students. These
are four ways to treat students.
This is a high kind of morality.
Treating your students well is a
high kind of
morality. And here are the four ways. They are
called the Four Ways. The name in
the ancient language is Four Ways to
Unite Your Students. That's called
Four Ways to Unite Your Students.
The
first one isn't in the book, so I
took it from another book,
and this is one by
Jon. It's called The Ocean of Reasoning.
It's a
commentary by
Nagar. If I weren't an old man who
spent two years translating the commentary...  They
're about Chandra Kirti, and if he hadn't
had anything else to
do, he wouldn't have been able to do 12 years in the
book. It's going to
be 3,000 pages or something like that, and he
says, "Here's the thing:
attract your students. Attract
your students with your generosity.
Give them money for a small answer."
Okay, and just be super generous with your
students all the time. So,
my teacher was really good at that.
That's how he got me started.
And well, it
always means that the student
comes to class, and it's a
class. One means dry. It's a
dry class, which means there's no snack.
Another means a wet class, which
means there are good
snacks. This is a class where there
are snacks, where there are no
snacks. It's dry, wet, either
way. So, attract your students
by being super generous, super generous with
your students, and I learned that from my
teacher. And you
know, we buy
things, we buy
cars. We have a friend, Dr. W. He's really
good at helping students.
Anything they need, he
helps them.
This is the first of the four
types of high morality: taking care
of your students and
attracting them. Anything they like,
study.  Find out what your students
like, find out what they like to take, what they like to
drink,
what they like to do. Study it. They should
be like you. Your students are your teachers. You
should study your students,
see what they like, and then attract them
like a bee to
honey. How does that work? What does the bee do? What does the bee say? What does
the
bee say? What does the bee
say? What's up,
bee? It's like saying it in
English. I'm going to give you a little something. What does it
mean? There's a
bee that first finds out what
your students like and gives it to them. And in fact, you can
go bankrupt. I've been
bankrupt
many times. We were talking in New
York when I started out, and well, I was
bankrupt many times. I had $0 in
debt, which would be like $0 now. What would
be like $0 now when
we finished the Diamond Way courses.
Because I paid for everything, I
remember,
with debt, and it took me many years to
pay it off just because I fed everyone.
Everyone was happy, so happy. So don't
be stingy. Don't worry about it.
Karma.  Karma will come back, it takes
a little time, but it will come back.
Karma doesn't open up in a
day, but you'll never lose money. If
you support your students, you'll always
be happy, you'll always have wealth, you'll
always be comfortable.
So take care of your students. If
you have to spend money, spend money. You don't even have to
worry, just do it.
Shut up and do it. Take care of
your students, whatever they
need, take care of them. It's
very, very
fun. All of Buddhism is very fun.
I think we should call it
hilarious and not Buddhism. If
you really understand Buddhism, it's a lot of
fun, like partying all day, giving
lots of compliments to your
students. So smart, I've never had a
student
like that. I
think you helped a grandmother, it
must be
a... and well, anything you do is
like having a
child, like having a
child. All the moms
are always praising their children, "Wow, you're the
smartest kid in the whole city." I don't know,
I'm so lucky to have you, to be your
mom. And well, actually, don't lie, just do it
a little bit extra, a
little bit.
And
use them.  Be happy, have fun, and for every
little thing they do, tell them, "Oh, you're so
smart." Then they make 10
mistakes. Don't say anything. It's just like having
a new kid. We're with Sofi, bye on
break. She does this for her
daughter. So, emphasize, encourage your
students. Yes, they do 10 things wrong. Every
time they do one good thing, but if you
're talking about the bad things, they're
never going to improve and they're not going to be
happy. Wait, sometimes you have to
wait a long time for the
student to do something right, and then you're going to
say, "Wow, you're my best student ever! I can't
believe it!"
So, emphasize, this is Buddhism,
real Buddhism: be generous with your
students. If you go bankrupt
with your students, you're
a good teacher. I've gone bankrupt many times.
Even these days, that bag is
completely empty. I want to give money to
whoever cleaned my room, and I said, "Oh, I already gave it."
And secondly,
no, so just encourage. Every
time they do something
good, tell them, "Wow, you're the best
kid in
town!" I think I was the principal.
Thirdly, say,
repeat, this means:
Don't
tolerate it if your students don't say it.  They don't do
what they say.
Impulses them to actually do something. Don't let them
be lazy. That means it's not
enough to have a class of
L and teach them for 14 years and have the
student do nothing. Then you're not
a good teacher. So
educate yourself so that they do something, okay? That's
a big
difference. We're not trying to create
Buddhist academics; we're trying to
create Buddhist people. So
make sure they do it, and every time they
do something, say, "
That's wonderful!"
Impulses them to bring Buddhism into their lives and
not just carry Buddhism in their mouths. Do
you understand? Number four, the most difficult one: you do
n't respond. You're a teacher, this
young lady, please.
Very good. 100. An
example of your
own: practice what you teach as a
teacher. The highest kind of morality
for a teacher
is to do what you say. And
simply as personal advice, being
a
teacher and not following what you're
teaching is schizophrenia. It's very
uncomfortable; it's going to drive you crazy. You're going to go
crazy. So you sit in the classroom and
say, "Everyone
should do the
reading book at night." If you don't...  So what do
you do then? I really think you
become
schizophrenic, you become a
crazy person. It's not healthy to teach
Buddhism if you're not doing it yourself. You're going to
become unhappy, you're going to
be more
unhappy. It's very
uncomfortable because it happened to me in my life.
If you're not following what you're
teaching, it's
very uncomfortable. You're going to feel dirty,
you're going to feel very dirty. So
number four, the
highest advice for a
teacher is: do what you do. And if you can't do it,
then shut up and don't do it.
But then don't talk about
it. And it's not
easy, like an
old man, an
old master. Keep working on yourself, never
give up, keep working to
do what you say, and never be
satisfied, and never give up. Say, "
Oh, I can't do that." I'm
teaching you to eliminate your
electronics, but secretly I have
my phone every night and I see things. It's going to drive you
crazy. So try to
stop yourself from doing what you say. And I'm going to
tell you something, like a teacher, and I actually
do what I teach so far, but what
I'm saying, if you don't, if
you have a secret, if you don't want your
students to know, you're not following
your own teachings. It's going to be very
awkward,
and the students can smell it, they can
feel it. It's like, "
Oh, 10
pm, put your phone away, don't look at that
stuff after 10 pm." And then the
student is like, "Something awkward here,
they can
tell." Nobody's a perfect
liar. You always have a kind of liar. You feel it. You
naturally show when you
're not telling the truth, like a teacher.
Everyone knows. I'm sorry.
Okay, on one hand, the teacher who doesn't
want to change becomes more and
more capable of hiding their mistakes.
On the other hand, just fix the
damn mistake and that's it. And then everyone
's happy. Then you can stand up
with pride and say, "I gave my computer
to Rob every night at 10 pm. I didn't see
my computer after 10 pm for
a year since I started." And you can smell it when
the teacher is telling you the truth,
and you can smell when they're not telling
the truth. So don't try to hide
something, just clean it up. You ca
n't. It's
like, when it's not, how can you
avoid it?  So your mom sees your room dirty, or you have to clean it.
And it's easier to clean it.
So we have to have integrity
as teachers. We have to do what we
say. And well, we're not perfect. We're going
to make mistakes. And I'm not saying you
should stop studying. I'm saying you
should clean more each
day, better and better each day. Nobody is a
perfect teacher. No teacher is
perfect except my teacher.
But anyway, I'm just saying we all
make mistakes. And let's be honest. If you
stand up and say, "I'm a teacher, I'm a
Buddhist teacher, and I make this mistake," for
example, "I had an abortion when I was
young, very young." So I'm telling
people, I don't try to
hide it. So be honest, people
can read it, and then you're a better
teacher. The teacher who makes mistakes is
better than the teacher who pretends they don't
make mistakes. Okay, you got that.
Very good.
Next, now he has an
interesting list. They are 11 different ways in which you
can
help
students. They are 11
suggestions of things you can do
to help your students. Number
one: help
people with things they have to do.
Work hard for your
students, and when your students
have problems,
show up. Stay there. Show up when they need you.  If your
students have problems, I have a
student who has cancer
now, and my wife and I
invite them home more frequently,
much more than before. And "show up"
means being there for them, being there to
help them. This word means being
there to share their problems, being
there for people.
Now, if you have 38,000
students, 138 students might not be
able to answer every email. It's not possible.
I have 500,000 emails
waiting for me. Don't go crazy, but
as much as possible, stay there,
be present for your
students. If not, try to have
someone who is there for them, but be
careful and take care of your students.
Pay special attention to
people who don't know how to do something they should be doing.
For example, if you have a
cafe in a small town and the manager does
n't know how to make money, apparently,
and loses your money every day, then
teach them. Then, very politely
and happily,
take them to another restaurant, have
dinner with them, and say, "Look, it seems you do
n't know how to do the finances," and they
say, "Yes, I don't really know." And then help
them. There is a  Special karma of
teaching people to do things they don't
know how to do, that's a special kind
of karma. Number three
[Music]
Always, always return the kindness,
the kindness that someone has
given you. As teachers, we return that kindness. We do
n't just say, "Oh well, thank you
for the donation." Next
year, really think about it and
show your
gratitude and help them
too. Number four:
If you are seeing someone who has
depression or fear,
then slow down and pay
special attention to
them. If you have
many
students, find someone who
can
help them, someone who is
afraid or has problems in their life.
Number four:
Especially people who have had
a loss in their life, who have
lost a member of their family, or have
lost their finances, or their home, or their
good health. Then especially
pay attention to those people who
are sad, that something has happened to them in their
life and that they are
sad. This word means "choca," which
in Sanskrit
means "the king who has no."
If someone is suffering in this
way because they lost someone in their
family, pay special attention to them as a
teacher. Especially do the things that
A teacher has to do everything. The teacher is going to
be very, very, very
busy. They're not going to sleep, and they're going to
break their morale. The
teacher's responsibility is to do everything and then
rest at the same
time.
Okay, the real teacher has to
learn. They pay special attention to
poor people. Pay special attention to
poor people, people who have
lost their country. We have friends from
Ukraine. My wife and
I sponsor these students, and it's
difficult; it's a lot of money, but we really
help them, and it turns out they've made us very, very
happy. We've really had a
very sweet time with them. They're wonderful, and they've
done a wonderful job in
our community. Very well, the
seventh one: there's a special karma for a
teacher who makes sure that their
students, or who pays attention to
people who don't have a place to
stay, that's called naga. This
means, for example, if someone is
building their
house, or someone is repairing their house, or
someone has lost their house or is in the
process of doing so, then pay special
attention to them as a teacher. In a special way,
pay
attention to every animal in this world. Every animal in this world
should have its own little house,
its own little cave, wherever it is. It does
n't matter if it's a human, an animal, or
a little mouse; everyone should have a
little place.  Where to go is their home,
and if you find an animal or
a student who doesn't have a
place—in English
we say they don't have a place, a place to
call home—then find them a place.
That's a special task. As a teacher,
make sure people find
a home, and the same goes for animals.
We adopted a kitten
last week. Look here, here are the little fists.
She kissed me. Look here,
she's a little wild. She's a little
wild. So we're getting to
know each other. Okay, so
homeless people, homeless animals—pay
special attention to them.
Next, people are having
fights in their group or in their marriage or
somewhere else, among their peers.
So, as a teacher, as a
Buddhist teacher who is learning the
perfection of morality, then
pay special attention to uniting
people, uniting people who are
having
conflict. A Buddhist has a
sensitive nose. I don't have a sensitive nose.
My wife has to tell me, "You haven't
changed your shirt for two weeks," and I
say, "No, nothing." And she says, "Your nose doesn't
work." It's interesting because if she
bakes a cake or something, I
can read that immediately, but I have to
change my pants.  It's like she
says,
you could pantones dequier, because you
have to have a good nose for
detecting problems. If you're in a
group, especially a Buddhist group,
and there are some people who aren't getting along,
or some husband or wife aren't getting along,
then a Buddhist would do something. A
Buddhist doesn't just arrive and see; they're going to try
to do something; they're going to try to help. Oh,
this group, two people... these two
people don't get along. And then they're going to
try to help.
Whether you succeed or not isn't the question.
Like, if a couple isn't having
problems, and the husband fights with the
wife, and the wife fights with the husband,
you have to try your best
to help them, but you can't
fix their karma. You can't fix their
karma. Some people just
have the karma to make each other
miserable year after year
after year. They have good teachers, but they ca
n't fix them. You can't
fix other people's problems.
But you have to try. It's a difference,
right? You understand? There's a
difference. As a teacher,
especially, your responsibility is to
try, but their karma is their karma, and you ca
n't fix it. They have to.
Only they can fix it. If
someone else could fix your karma, there wouldn't be
people dying in this world because...
Buddhas have already been here. Buddha
was already here and she did an excellent
job, but people keep
dying. Buddha can't stop it.
People keep getting divorced. Buddha can't stop it.
You can stop things, right?
So do your best. Try to
help them. That's your responsibility. And do
n't get discouraged if it doesn't work. You have to keep trying, trying, trying.
And
people are going to keep getting divorced, and
people are going to keep fighting within
a Buddhist group. And it's like, okay,
then smile. Try again tomorrow.
This is all you can
do. Buddha can't
fix them either. Do your best, but do
n't drive yourself crazy doing it. Do your
best. Take an interest in them. Oh, guys, it
looks like you're having problems. Yes, I
can help. No. Okay, okay,
next. If you see someone
doing something nice, stop and help them.
Wow, I like that project. You guys
are doing really well.
Well, I didn't know this
young lady. I have a friend named [name missing]. You
know her? Sometimes I ask her to come to
my house and help us clean. She
came yesterday and helped us clean the
class. She cleaned some rose bushes because they're
growing around the house, and she
has these.  She cut these flowers, and
she's like, she's trying
to help us, and she
says, "Your house is... your house is... it's confusing.
You have to make your house more
organized. Then you'll find the
things you're looking for,
and you'll be happier if your house
is more organized. I have a book for you."
And she gave me this book by Mari Condo.
She's a Japanese woman who writes, "
How to Organize Your House." I would never do it,
but my friend, who I
hired to organize my house, she
came and organized everything. Now I can't
find
anything, but then she said, "There's
a card that says, 'This is here.'
She made a map of my
house, and actually, I use it very
frequently. Where the heck is it?" So
she read this book.
Actually, there's a Netflix series by Mari
Condo, and I have the honor of giving a
talk with her this week. What a
day! I really appreciate whoever
took that picture where old
Gela looks so young and has so much
hair. But anyway, you're all completely
welcome to come. We did a show
together before. She's very... she's very
cool. We really enjoyed our time together,
and we did some promotion, and I'd like to
thank Sofi Chao for doing it.
[Music]
Okay. Anyway, if someone is
doing something
good, if someone is helping a lot of
people, then give them support. One
thing is helping people whose
house is being bombed in
a war, that's important, but
also, if you see someone doing something
good, make a donation or help them.
Tell them, "Do you need help? I like what you're
doing. What you're doing
is really cool, and I'm going to help you."
And then give them help.
Now, the next thing: If you see the
opposite, if you see people getting into
trouble, then say
something or do
something. And
I have a personality...
My wife told me, "
I like to tease other people.
Then some people
do something wrong, and I don't say anything. And
then they do something worse, and I still don't say anything. And
then they get into big trouble." And I still don't
say anything. And my wife says, "That's
not kind. You should say something if
someone is doing something wrong. You know,
all human beings do
n't know you're a Buddhist teacher or
that. It doesn't matter. Every human being... If you see
someone doing something that's going to
hurt them or hurt
other people, then you should say
something. You should get
involved. Don't be afraid to get
involved. I'm not over-inventing you either.
Very politely, you can say something.
Very well, that's number 10.
Number 11 is when the time comes to
perform a miracle to help other
people. You should do it. You must
do it, like flying in the
sky or lifting a car with your... your...
time... other
miracles." And she has a comment that is
very sweet: "We
can do all of this except
number 11." And then she says, "As
this
list is an ancient Buddhist list, it has
11 parts. Number 11 is if you can't
do it yet."  Don't worry, don't
worry about it, let it go for now.
But
remember, when the day comes that you can
fly in the
sky, or that you can lift a building
with a tiny finger, if you can help
someone, you have to take
responsibility for doing it. If you are capable of
performing a miracle, then you should do it. You have
a responsibility to
do it when the time comes, when
the time is right, not just to
brag.
Okay, okay,
all forms of helping other
people are included in the third
type of morality. Okay, which is the word I just
said: helping other people.
So, it's interesting that in
English, in the United States, morality
means not killing, not stealing, not lying. In
Buddhism, doing good things for other
people is a second level of
morality, and doing good things in an
ultimate way for other people is the
highest type of morality. Take them to
meditate, take them to think about
emptiness. That is the highest type
of morality.
Okay, even if you're not in the mood to
take them to have all this, at
least light the top 10 seeds and do
not harm
others when you start following
miso.  You start doing things for other
people. In Buddhism, we call that
morality. When you're trying to
improve yourself and you're trying to help
other people, that's
morality. How long do I have to stop
teaching? In 20 minutes, 30 minutes. We'll
finish the perfection of an
ethical life. Now let's start the
perfection of not getting angry.
Okay, this one's
tough. They call it patience, but I get
impatient with this
word. It's not like you just sit there like that.
I don't get angry often. My friends
know it. It's very rare that they see me really
angry, but I do get
annoyed. And this isn't talking about
anger; it's talking about getting annoyed.
Okay, you can keep the vow of
Bodhisattva. You get angry, you almost
never get annoyed. Well, that's different. I get
annoyed at the airport, and I get
annoyed in taxis, in restaurants, and
in hotels. I can't believe they can
clean it at 3:30. What's wrong with
that? Well, by the way, I didn't get angry, I didn't get
annoyed, I just got a little
heated. Okay, this is the next
perfection. What number perfection is it?
Number
three. I don't like to call it patience.
Patience, for me, is like, you have to  Going to the
bathroom and there's someone in the bathroom.
So it's like,
that's patience, not getting upset. It's
a different thing because things go
wrong all day, things happen all
day. You can stay calm and cool, and
as a Buddhist, you can stay in a
good mood when things aren't
going well. You can laugh at
yourself, you can have
fun when bad things are
happening, when crap is
happening, like your car breaks down. Me and
Stanley have a nice car, that's very
classic. We go down a hill, we go down it,
and then we have fun.
I think we clean up the
mess in less than two minutes. We were
gone in two
minutes. We let someone else do it.
That's a tradition in our
group,
Sonia. So anyway,
now this is so beautiful. What is
the essence of patience? Buddhism has
two parts. There are two parts. Number one
is what we call patience in English,
which means when someone
hurts you, you don't get upset. When someone
hurts you, you don't get
upset. You know, like, something does something. You
're like,
okay. And then there's the second part of
Buddhist patience. It's something I
'm really very interested in. I love Buddhism,
frankly, so much. The second  Part of
this perfection
is being able to be
patient with the problems that Samara
brings you, like
surgery. You have medical problems, and the
doctor says, "We can fix that. You're going to do it. We're going to cut you.
In fact, we're going
to cut you twice." And I say, "
Can you finish it the first time?" And he says, "
No, no, no, no, you're not going to be able to
handle it. The pain is too much. We have to
do it 50/50." So we're going to cut you, then you're going
to feel better, and
then we're going to cut you again. And then they say, "I
ask them, do I have another
alternative?" And they say, "No." And I say, "Well, that
sounds good." And then there's a kind of
Buddhist attitude toward pain in
life. If you're alive, you're going to have pain.
Okay, if you're alive, the sign that you're dead
is that the pain has stopped.
Okay, if your pain has stopped, that's the
definition of being dead. Before
that time, you have to be patient with
two things. The first is with idiots. I do
n't know how many countries there are in the
world, but there's one extra country
called the Nation of Idiots, and they're everywhere.
I think they have a
free visa. It's like the
Idiot Visa. So that's the first thing
where you...  Buddhist patience is being
patient with the people who give you
trouble. That's only 50% of
patience. The other 50% of patience is
enjoying it when they tell you you have two
operations. In
fact, I think I can say that
when we went to
that doctor's office, everyone
was happy to see us. We made
everyone happy. We're very good at
it. Roby and I worked with those
grumpy doctors and those
grumpy nurses. And now, when we go for the
other
operation, it's so good to see you and cut me out,
honey. And we both know there's no other
option. You have to do it. It's a
medical treatment. You have to do it.
So we have fun. Why not? Why do
you have to be so serious about it? You do
n't have any other
option. You have to do it.
And we have so much fun. We even had
fun during the
surgery. The whole process was fun. It was fun.
And
listen, there's no
reason why you have to be unhappy
when you're in pain because it's going to come. The
pain is going to come, and you can't stop it.
Everyone in this room—I'm just
the leader, I'm the
first one—is going to have this
pleasure. So have fun. Why not? You can't.
Get out of there if you have a
human body things are going to happen if you live in
this world if you have a business if you
have children if you have a mother
parents if you live in a house in a
country on
earth you're going to have at
some point please take it with
grace be
happy it's not like you have to sit
and cut yourself off like to have for that
Oh I'm so happy told me to be
happy No no I'm not saying that I'm
saying life is going to bring you problems the way
you tell you that
a person is a Buddhist person is that they
know how to laugh in the face of problems
your car broke down I
knew it Yeah it happened to me last week I have
a
squirrel loves to eat like all the
engineering inside my car and it
did it like three
or four times it was
6000 The pipe inside the engineering
is made of plastic that is made of
peanut oil and it was like yum yum
And then it's like every time it does it's
like 5000 6000 and I'm like, oh my
god what are you going to do am I going to kill it
no By the way  I caught it, I took it to
another
neighbor's house, that's sharing the teaching.
So we have two divisions there.
Number one, people are going to cause you
problems, that's patience, obviously, but
life is going to cause you problems. A Buddhist
also has to be in a good mood
about it. In fact, a Buddhist can't
tell, you can't guess if
the squirrel ate part of their car or
if they won the lottery because they're going to
look the same. If someone gives them $0 or if a
squirrel cost them $0 because it ate their
car, a real Buddhist looks the same. Oh, the same thing happened.
What happened to the $0 or
the squirrel? The squirrel,
the squirrel. And what are you going
to
do? Why get
angry? You're just going to have a
heart attack and it doesn't help anyone.
Okay, you understand now. It's
a perfect logical argument that's
impossible to
make. I have a little more
time. This is beautiful. This is beautiful.
This is... I don't know, it's like the
most beautiful thing. It really is the most
beautiful thing. You should read it every night, every night before going to sleep.
Like Lin.
The idiots in the world are
countless, there is no end.
Okay, take care.  One by one, three by three they appear, they're
like
cockroaches in your
house. Listen, an old man
tells you, the old man tells the
young ones, there are many idiots,
probably a billion. When you're born they line up,
every day of your life a
new one
comes, they're not going to run out before
you die.
Okay, you can fight with them, you can
try to hurt them, you can kick them
out of your house, you can make sure they do
n't come back to your country, you can do
these things, one by one,
hurt all those idiots that
appear in your life, and you're going to die
before you're done.
Trust me, there are
a million in line and they're
waiting for you, every one is waiting
for you, they're
there. You can't
physically get rid of all of them
before you die, you don't have time. If you
did nothing else, if you didn't make
dinner, if you didn't
bathe, if you didn't do your meditation, and you
just
dedicated yourself to going with each
idiot, they wouldn't run out before
you died. You'd still be
doing the last day of your life. Therefore, it's
more
logical to take care of them or pay attention.  of
responsibility for your patience before
don't try to go one by one after those
idiots and
hurt them
hurt your anger work on your anger
for 000 we have 000 I have to
borrow Well tomorrow I
pay you for 000 are ready everyone
woke up for
000 what is the famous ex example of
shantia about trying to stop
all the people who
hurt you there is a system you raise your
hand and take the microphone no I simply
give money I
told them if they make a mistake they have to
pay me 000 No no no I'm not
praising that is a great shantia line
unfortunately not the one I'm
looking for but I honor you
IB never makes a
mistake very
complicated very well cancel the
shoe put hell you
understand you can't stop every
irritating person in the world listen to me I'm an
old man and I've tried and I'm
fast and I can't stop all the
irritating people in fact they're still in
line waiting for me so just
stop your anger And then it's done you're done
the rest of your life you're in a
good mood okay agreed you can't
stop every person who hurt you  It irritates you, you can't
cover the whole world with skin,
just put on some
shoes, take care of
yourself 100% because it was a Shant phrase
and you can destroy one eye, it's the same as
destroying all your
enemies, and in fact, if you don't work on your
anger, and if you don't
work on not getting angry, if you're not in a
good mood all the time,
all day long, even when they're
cutting you, give
me more of that anesthetic. That's good,
you know, it just starts to get worse and
worse and worse. It doesn't work, it doesn't
work to try to have all the
stupid people in your life because
when you try, they're going to multiply
because that's karma.
So, there's something in
Sanskrit called
tapas. There are two tapas here. One means "
tapas" in Spanish.
I like that one. But
there's another tapas in Sanskrit that
means a
difficult spiritual practice in India. In some
Hindu groups, for
example, you raise your arm for 20 years
until your arm case disappears, and
then you sit in a circle of
fire and see how long you can
stay there, and then you're supposed to
be some kind of special person.
Buddhism. Sit with an idiot for 10
minutes, 20 minutes, all day. Marry
them. Let's see if you can do it.
I think that's what my
wife did. A Buddhist doesn't try to avoid
people who annoy him. A Buddhist
tries to connect with
them. Do you want to come work with
me? Yes, yes, because, yes, because I've never met
anyone as much of an idiot as
you. I've never met anyone who can
help me with my anger. Do you understand? Have fun.
Buddhism isn't that
serious. Oh, she
said I shouldn't get
angry.
Okay, one
more picture. No, not that.
48.10 Here we go.
Okay, from my heart I tell you
this: I finished a new level. It's going to be
ready in
November. Course Launch 4 is going to be
ready in December. And basically,
Advanced Level 4 is called How to Double Your
Productivity. How to do
twice as much business, twice as much
family
life stuff, how to get twice as much done.
And people ask me, a lot of
people have asked me, how do you do so many things?
How do you do that?
You know,
how do you manage to do so many things? I
have 42 companies,
okay, and I run them all, and I'm  Happy and
relaxed, they say,
how do I do it?
Because I don't waste time with
idiots. I mean it, and I'm sorry if I'm
using bad language, but my
wife isn't here. So, I can, and
nobody's going to tell you, okay? I'm
going to tell you a secret to
your productivity. I'm going to tell you the
secret to success in your
productivity: Don't give idiots
a minute of your day. Someone says something mean
to you, and you're like, "Ha, okay, fine,
bye." Someone cheats on you, and you're like, "Oh
man, I hope I never see you
again. Goodbye." I don't fight with
people. I don't waste my time. My friends
know this. I'm just not interested
in it. I learned the secret of life: I
let them be idiots, and I let them
go their own way
because the worst thing about an idiot is
spending time with them. So I don't
spend time fighting with them. Someone
hurts me, and I'm like, "Okay, see you in
the next life. Don't be
late." I mean, I don't worry about it, and I
really encourage you as
young people, from the advice of an
old man who has had a very
productive life. Someone asks me, "My
lawyer..."  He asked me, "Are you getting
old? You've had all
these surgeries. You have to tell
your wife, 'Where are your things?'" And I
'm like, "Oh yeah,
thanks." "How many books have you
written?" And I said, "I don't know. And you can
make a list in case you die."
I'm like, "Okay, that's
126 books,
okay." And he says, "Oh God, how did you do that?" And I
say, "I don't fight with people
when they're mean to me or
not nice to me or complain
or want to fight
with me." I'm like, "Hehe, sorry, I have to
write another book. I'm going to fight
with you tomorrow. Come back tomorrow, and really,
please, please, your life is going to
be so much more pleasant. Someone wants to
fight with you, someone wants to cause you
trouble, then." And I'm like, "Oh, okay, that's
cool. Do you have something to say to me? I'm listening."
And well, I'll go there
while they complain, I'll write another book.
Okay. What perfection is that? The third,
the third perfection? We haven't finished
with it. We're going to finish it tomorrow, but
from my
heart, this life is very precious, and this
life is very beautiful. It's not about
unhappy people ruining your life.
Just tell them  Okay, this is good.
They want to fight you. Okay, that's good. It
sounds good. I
see you. There are two ultimate and secret methods: the
Diamond Way. Everyone
tells me, "Please, will you teach me the
Diamond Way?" You want to do something from Camp
Diamond? Now,
problems? Tell them, "Oh, I'm going, I'll be right back. I'm
going to the bathroom." Nobody ever stops you. So you don't
leave the bathroom. Then write a
book while you're in the bathroom. That's
the first method. What's the second
method? Oh, this is really cool. If your family
is having a fight at Christmas,
the holidays, well, at
Chinese New Year, and everyone wants to have a
fight, people drink a lot. And then if they
're fighting in the kitchen, take a glass
of water. When the fight gets really
serious, throw it. Just
throw it. There's glass everywhere, and
everyone, everyone, watch out, watch out, nobody
move. And then you clean up the glass, and
everyone forgets about fighting.
These are the secrets of an old man.
This is my secret method. I tell you,
this Diamond Way, you practice the
Diamond Way, bathroom and glass. Cause
and effect.
Okay, just change
people's focus and just distract
people and don't waste your time.
Listen, you don't have time to be angry
with people. You're going to die, you're going to
die, I'm telling you. I never thought I'd get
old and now I am.
You're going to get old too. Don't
waste your time. Your time is the most
precious thing you have. Your time is
priceless. Your time is worth a million
dollars a
minute. Don't give it to stupid people.
Don't give it to them and tell them, "I love you." Go bother
someone else. I'm
busy. I have other things to do. Don't
fight with people, it's a huge
waste of time, a huge
waste of time. Okay, see you
tomorrow. Very well.